<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ada K Hagan, PhdD</title>
    <link>https://akhagan.com/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://akhagan.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Ada K Hagan, PhdD</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2023 16:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://akhagan.com/media/icon_huc429f2fc0b4e7d8d8064836fcb38b408_31117_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Ada K Hagan, PhdD</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gender Bias in Publishing in ASM Journals</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/talk/gender-bias-in-publishing-in-asm-journals/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2023 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/talk/gender-bias-in-publishing-in-asm-journals/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overview of a Gender-based Analysis of Publishing Outcomes</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/talk/overview-of-a-gender-based-analysis-of-publishing-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/talk/overview-of-a-gender-based-analysis-of-publishing-outcomes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equal Opportunities in Microbiology Journals Don&#39;t Start at Submission</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/talk/equal-opportunities-in-microbiology-journals-dont-start-at-submission/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2022 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/talk/equal-opportunities-in-microbiology-journals-dont-start-at-submission/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The U.S. academic job market survives the SARS-CoV-2 global pandemic</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/publication/kozik-preprint-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/publication/kozik-preprint-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Desk reject from &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;. Available at bioRxiv as a preprint!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equal Opportunities in Microbiology Journals</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/talk/equal-opportunities-in-microbiology-journals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 13:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/talk/equal-opportunities-in-microbiology-journals/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ten simple rules to increase computational skills among biologists with Code Clubs</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/publication/ten-simple-rules-to-increase-computational-skills/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 11:58:58 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/publication/ten-simple-rules-to-increase-computational-skills/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Women Are Underrepresented and Receive Differential Outcomes at ASM Journals: a Six-Year Retrospective Analysis</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/publication/women-are-underrepresented-and-receive-differential-outcomes-at-asm-journals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 11:57:51 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/publication/women-are-underrepresented-and-receive-differential-outcomes-at-asm-journals/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Petrobactin protects against oxidative stress and enhances sporulation efficiency in Bacillus anthracis Sterne</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/publication/hagan-petrobactin-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/publication/hagan-petrobactin-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Petrobactin Is Exported from Bacillus anthracis by the RND-Type Exporter ApeX</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/publication/hagan-petrobactin-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/publication/hagan-petrobactin-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flying under the radar: The non-canonical biochemistry and molecular biology of petrobactin from Bacillus anthracis</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/publication/hagan-petrobactin-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/publication/hagan-petrobactin-2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversity Statement</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/project/dei-statement/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/project/dei-statement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My thoughts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Growing up poor, there were few things my family could afford and any complaint about
fairness received my father&amp;rsquo;s patented response: &amp;ldquo;Life isn&amp;rsquo;t fair.&amp;rdquo; I never dared to voice my internal reply of &amp;ldquo;But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean it shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the acknowledgment that life isn&amp;rsquo;t fair, I still held the assumption that my country was fair. Everyone had the right to vote and access to capitalism, which meant that hard work always led to success. If it didn&amp;rsquo;t, then you were doing something wrong. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until my graduate career at the University of Michigan that I learned otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014, I traveled to Ethiopia in my first international experience. There, I taught immunology and microbiology to medical students who had only recently learned English and who had different values, experiences, and assumptions than I did. Not only did I learn a lot about teaching and how to navigate interactions with other cultures, but I also learned the isolation that comes with being visibly different from your peers and how privileged I was just by virtue of my birth country. This experience led me to question my career goals and laid the foundation for what I would learn in the years to come, that a couple of laws don&amp;rsquo;t change the backbone of a country founded on inequity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scientific literature is finally catching up to the personal experiences of underrepresented minorities in academia, documenting that implicit biases, and systems designed to support white men, repeatedly fail nearly all other demographics. Potential inequities lay at nearly all steps from childhood through academic administration and limit the access of less privileged individuals to &amp;ldquo;successful&amp;rdquo;
academic careers. This isn&amp;rsquo;t fair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Returning to the States, the first problem I noticed, was how scientists speak to each other. The language and syntax used in academia is highly exclusionary, so I co-founded a student group that focused on translating and communicating science for non-experts. One of our most successful ventures was live-blogging a campus academic conference to make it accessible to scientists unable to attend as well as non-scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My passion for breaking down barriers in science, led to my postdoctoral fellowship in the journals department of the American Society for Microbiology (ASM). Here, I was given the opportunity to study the barriers and biases in the peer review process. Academic publishing is a cornerstone to academic careers and the decisions made by journal editors and reviewers have lasting impacts on careers. A literature review of the field left me angry at the seemingly endless documentations of bias. I was also mentally exhausted, but the experience has made me a stronger advocate for diversity, equity, and inclusion (DEI).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout my graduate career, I supported and mentored several undergraduate students from underrepresented groups in academia, made efforts to make science more accessible, and participated in programs for underrepresented groups, such as the McNair Scholars Program. However, since beginning my postdoctoral fellowship, I have begun making more thoughtful and concerted efforts to improve fairness through DEI. I&amp;rsquo;ve suggested and helped brainstorm department-wide DEI discussions that led to action items adopted by my department at UM. I helped draw attention to and improve
invited speaker diversity by compiling data on previous invited speakers and presenting my findings to the department faculty. I&amp;rsquo;ve also become active in the department DEI committee and the broader UM DEI community through completion of a professional development certificate focusing on DEI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These efforts are small, and only a beginning, but they are the foundation of what I believe should be everyone&amp;rsquo;s life work - making life as fair as it can be.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Altering the Academic Ecosystem: Graduate Education Reports Propose Critical Reforms</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/post/altering-the-academic-ecosystem-graduate-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/post/altering-the-academic-ecosystem-graduate-education/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examining Flint: New research highlights lack of legionella public policy</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/post/examining-flint/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/post/examining-flint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been three years and 11 months since the residents of Flint, Michigan have had clean drinking water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the city water source was switched from Lake Huron to the Flint River in April 2014, residents fell victim to corrosive, lead-contaminated water. Exposure to and consumption of that water through October 2015—when the water source was switched back—has led to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cnn.com/2017/01/31/health/iyw-flint-water-crisis-two-years-later/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;learning and developmental delays&lt;/a&gt; and correlates with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/next/body/flint-water-tied-to-fetal-death-and-lower-fertility-rates/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;decreased fertility&lt;/a&gt;. The water switch is now linked to deaths caused by the bacterial pathogen &lt;em&gt;Legionella pneumophila&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Legionella&lt;/em&gt; are gram-negative bacteria found throughout nature, where they infect amoebae. However, they can also live in built environments, such as reservoirs and water towers, where they form persistent biofilms from which bacteria are dispersed. When the water is used, people are exposed to the bacteria by inhaling aerosolized water droplets like those produced by showers and sprinkler systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once in the lungs, legionellae can cause the infection known as Legionnaires’ disease. The bacteria invade and replicate in lung macrophages, which provide a replication environment similar to that in their amoebae hosts. Unchecked, the infection leads to pneumonia and a 10-&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-11/documents/ndwactechforlegionellaslides.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;30% chance&lt;/a&gt; of death, primarily in those with compromised immune systems, including those over 50 and current or former smokers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although at least 24 species of &lt;em&gt;Legionella&lt;/em&gt; are associated with human disease, about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1128/CMR.00052-09&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;90% of Legionnaires&amp;rsquo; cases&lt;/a&gt; are caused by &lt;em&gt;Legionella pneumophila&lt;/em&gt;. This is the organism that University of Michigan professor and ASM President Elect Michele Swanson researches. Her work has focused on how legionellae replicate inside macrophages, evade degradation, and, more recently, persist in the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Swanson’s expertise in legionellae and proximity to Flint meant she was ready and able to join a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.michigan.gov/documents/snyder/FWICC_Meeting_FACHEP_Presentation1-July_8_2016_528953_7.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;multidisciplinary&lt;/a&gt; team created to study the effects of changes in the Flint water source on public health. This research group, the Flint Area Community Health and Environment Partnership (&lt;a href=&#34;http://flint.wayne.edu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;FACHEP&lt;/a&gt;), also includes researchers from the Henry Ford Health System, Michigan State University, Colorado State University, the MADE Institute, Genesee Health Systems, and Kettering University. FACHEP was created in January 2016, when Michigan Governor Rick Snyder organized a  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mlive.com/news/flint/index.ssf/2018/02/flint_legionnaires_researchers.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;$3.35-million contract&lt;/a&gt; with the Michigan Department of Health and Human Services (MDHHS) and Wayne State University to fund the collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the Flint water crisis, there were 6 to 12 Legionnaires’ disease cases in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2018/02/05/582482024/lethal-pneumonia-outbreak-caused-by-low-chlorine-in-flint-water&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;typical year&lt;/a&gt; in the Flint area. When Flint’s source water was switched to the Flint River, there were 45 cases per year in 2014 and 2015. Nick Lyons, the former director of MDHHS, has been &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.npr.org/2017/06/14/532969059/two-top-michigan-officials-face-criminal-charges-over-flint-water-crisis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;charged with involuntary manslaughter&lt;/a&gt; for failing to respond to the Flint Legionnaires’ outbreak for more than a year, while the Chief Medical Executive, Dr. Eden Wells, has been charged with obstruction of justice. Wells has also been &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.detroitnews.com/story/news/michigan/flint-water-crisis/2017/06/18/flint-legionnaires-charges-emails-doctor/102994738/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;accused of interfering&lt;/a&gt; with research conducted by the FACHEP group. If the MDHHS can show that the outbreak was limited to patients and visitors to the McLaren hospital in Flint (which has been plagued by hospital-associated Legionnaires’ disease), then a guilty verdict might be avoided. However, FACHEP’s recently published research doesn’t support the hypothesis of the MDHHS, who despite providing funding for the FACHEP, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.michigan.gov/mdhhs/0,5885,7-339-73970_71692_71696-459450--,00.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;disputes&lt;/a&gt; the findings from both papers. That funding will no longer be available following a contract dispute and was announced the day following publication of Zahran et. al in PNAS.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-figure-1-chlorine-levels-before-during-and-after-the-switch-from-lake-huron-to-the-flint-river-used-with-permission-from-sourcehttpwwwdxdoiorg101073pnas1718679115-figure-1b&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Figure 1. Chlorine levels before, during, and after the switch from Lake Huron to the Flint River (used with permission from [source](http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1718679115), figure 1b).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/examining-flint/image_1_hu2262ab12c1caa29f39dfe32ae071ca4d_1675586_9419c7616511e94523fb618c1a5e5742.webp 400w,
               /post/examining-flint/image_1_hu2262ab12c1caa29f39dfe32ae071ca4d_1675586_0fd1a849835207de571e06441da4854a.webp 760w,
               /post/examining-flint/image_1_hu2262ab12c1caa29f39dfe32ae071ca4d_1675586_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://akhagan.com/post/examining-flint/image_1_hu2262ab12c1caa29f39dfe32ae071ca4d_1675586_9419c7616511e94523fb618c1a5e5742.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;546&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Figure 1. Chlorine levels before, during, and after the switch from Lake Huron to the Flint River (used with permission from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1718679115&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;, figure 1b).
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1718679115&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zahran et. al&lt;/a&gt;, compared cases of Legionnaires’ disease in Flint and surrounding areas over a six-year period (before, during, and after the Flint water switch) to chlorine levels at multiple locations in the city, and found compelling correlations. Before the water source was switched to the Flint River, chlorine levels at all eight locations clustered together with levels ranging between 0.2 and 1 mg/L. However, after the switch to Flint River water, the chlorine levels went haywire and fluctuated wildly between locations, ranging from almost 0 to 2.5 mg/liter (Figure 1). Levels restabilized after the water source was switched back to Lake Huron.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-figure-2-the-probability-of-legionnaires-disease-as-a-function-of-chlorine-levels-used-with-permission-from-sourcehttpwwwdxdoiorg101073pnas1718679115-figure-3&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Figure 2. The probability of Legionnaires’ disease as a function of chlorine levels. (used with permission from [source](http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1718679115), figure 3)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/examining-flint/image_2_hu24d3313c44e0b9a18ad9f460d71fbc7b_355328_9285c3832779046b5c8b26ce3c15afe7.webp 400w,
               /post/examining-flint/image_2_hu24d3313c44e0b9a18ad9f460d71fbc7b_355328_54fd0ac7582adbc2b5de7e70f74a50b7.webp 760w,
               /post/examining-flint/image_2_hu24d3313c44e0b9a18ad9f460d71fbc7b_355328_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://akhagan.com/post/examining-flint/image_2_hu24d3313c44e0b9a18ad9f460d71fbc7b_355328_9285c3832779046b5c8b26ce3c15afe7.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;510&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Figure 2. The probability of Legionnaires’ disease as a function of chlorine levels. (used with permission from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1718679115&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;, figure 3)
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the researchers plotted the probability of Legionnaires’ disease against Cl$_2$ levels they found that the chlorine concentration was predictive of disease occurrence. For chlorine to act as an effective disinfectant, it must be present as Cl$_2$ in levels of at least 0.2 mg/liter and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cdc.gov/safewater/chlorine-residual-testing.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;recommends 0.5 mg/liter&lt;/a&gt;. The odds of a person in Flint contracting Legionnaires’ disease increased by nearly threefold when the average weekly chlorine levels were below 0.5 mg/liter and by fourfold for weeks when chlorine was less than 0.2 mg/liter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researchers hypothesize that the organic matter in the Flint River, plus leached metals from pipe corrosion, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1718679115&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;likely bound the chlorine&lt;/a&gt; and caused the levels to dip dangerously low. The ineffectively low chlorine levels combined with warm summer temperatures, allowed legionellae to thrive, spiking known cases of Legionnaires’ disease in the third quarters of 2014 and 2015. While their data indicate that chlorine concentrations in the water were predictive of Legionnaires’ disease among Flint residents, the data do not rule out other factors contributing to bacterial growth, like the greater abundance of nutrients (iron and organic matter) in the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key part of the analysis in PNAS was to determine whether switching water sources in Flint led to an increased risk of Legionnaires’ disease. Researchers answered this question by comparing the occurrence of Legionnaires’ disease in Flint residents to disease occurrence in neighboring areas with a different water source. Comparing these data allowed researchers to determine odds ratios, or the likelihood that a random Flint resident would contract Legionnaires’ disease relative to residents of neighboring areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, the researchers determined that switching the water source to the Flint River made a Flint resident 6.3 times more likely to contract Legionnaires’ disease than someone not exposed to the water. However, in September 2014, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mlive.com/news/flint/index.ssf/2014/09/flint_expands_boil_water.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;boil water advisory&lt;/a&gt; was issued that caused residents to &lt;a href=&#34;https://phys.org/news/2018-03-economists-tracked-disease-flint-crisis.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;avoid Flint River city water&lt;/a&gt;, creating an interesting dynamic to examine. The researchers performed the same analysis, this time dividing Legionnaires’ cases into before and after the advisory. In this analysis, the odds ratio was 10 post-switch and pre-boil water advisory while the odds ratio was “only” 5.8 following the advisory. The odds of Legionnaires’ disease for Flint residents returned to normal (&amp;lt;1) when the water source was restored to Lake Huron. The researchers estimate that the city’s switch to the Flint River water was responsible for 80% of the reported cases of Legionnaires’ disease during that time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following publication, the MDHHS issued a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.michigan.gov/documents/mdhhs/MDHHS_Response_to_FACHEP_Proceedings_of_the_National_Academy_of_Sciences_Article_FINAL_613088_7.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;press release&lt;/a&gt; stating that use of the referral date (when the case was reported) instead of the symptom onset date introduces error. However, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.michigan.gov/documents/mdhhs/171108_KWR_2017.081_final_report_scoping_mission_DEF_613090_7.PDF&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;researchers maintain&lt;/a&gt; that this doesn’t affect the overall results. Swanson’s study is in agreement with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mlive.com/news/flint/index.ssf/2017/02/cdc_finds_first_genetic_link_b.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;similar conclusion&lt;/a&gt; reached in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1021/acs.estlett.6b00192&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a 2016 study&lt;/a&gt;.
In Flint between 2014 and 2015, 12 people died of Legionnaires and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2018/02/05/582482024/lethal-pneumonia-outbreak-caused-by-low-chlorine-in-flint-water&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;more than 80 fell ill&lt;/a&gt;. Those are only the known cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second FACHEP paper, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1128/mBio.00016-18&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;published in &lt;em&gt;mBio&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, compared clinical isolates obtained from Legionnaires’ cases in Southeast Michigan to legionellae isolated from homes in and around Flint. Byrne, et al. sampled plumbing (kitchen faucet, shower, and hot water heater) in 130 residences and isolated 2 non&amp;ndash; &lt;em&gt;pneumophila&lt;/em&gt; legionellae and 16 &lt;em&gt;L. pneumophila&lt;/em&gt; strains from 13 Flint residences. Two &lt;em&gt;L. pneumophila&lt;/em&gt; strains were also isolated from non-Flint residences. Their first step was to characterize the relatedness of the isolated strains. Phylogenetic analysis separated the clinical isolates into four different clonal populations, one of which belonged to the same clonal group as a single environmental isolate. All but one of the other environmental isolates belonged to a separate clonal group. Further characterization of the environmental isolates in Swanson’s lab found that while all 33 of the clinical isolates belonged to serogroup (SG) 1, the environmental isolates were predominantly SG 6. Additionally, the SG 6 isolates performed just as well as SG 1 isolates in laboratory tests for macrophage infectivity and replication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These findings are significant because they indicate that the clinical isolates are not related and likely have different initial sources, which means that the patients weren’t exposed to the same strain of legionellae in the same location and suggests that the outbreak was not hospital-associated. The data also support what is already commonly accepted in the legionellae field—that cases of Legionnaires’ are drastically underreported, and that SG 1 strains cause those that are reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MDHHS issued &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.michigan.gov/documents/mdhhs/MDHHS_Response_to_FACHEP_American_Society_for_Microbiology_mBio_Article_rev_21318_613639_7.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a press release&lt;/a&gt; disputing the possibility of under diagnosis and reporting of Legionnaires’ disease caused by plumbing isolates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the U.S., it’s estimated that as few as 5% of Legionnaires’ disease cases are documented. Clinically, there’s little need for detailed diagnosis, since most patients presenting with pneumonia are immediately prescribed antibiotics. Patients are only tested for a specific bacterial cause if they don’t respond to therapeutics. Drug resistance in Legionnaires’ disease is not yet an issue, but surveillance of the disease is severely hampered since failing to diagnose also fails to generate data that could be important for setting policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, detection presents a problem. Patient sputum samples are notoriously difficult to obtain, and legionellae are particularly finicky to culture, requiring special growth medium, an experienced lab technician, and several days for growth. Even when present in the sputum sample they may not grow, particularly if the patient is already receiving antibiotics for the pneumonia. According to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cdc.gov/legionella/clinicians/diagnostic-testing.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the CDC&lt;/a&gt;, culturing from sputum can positively identify 20-80% of cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The test of choice for Legionnaires’ disease detects &lt;em&gt;L. pneumophila&lt;/em&gt; antigen from the urine in more than 70% of cases. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1086/345529&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;urinary antigen test&lt;/a&gt; is rapid and isn’t immediately affected by administration of antibiotics, but it has its own severe limitations: it only reacts to SG 1 antigen, and some patients may be so ill that they &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bridgemi.com/children-families/soaring-pneumonia-deaths-genesee-county-likely-linked-undiagnosed-legionnaires&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;cannot produce urine&lt;/a&gt; for the test. There are other detection methods, but they suffer from cross-reactivity with other pathogens or aren’t available as a standardized assay. So, while there are at least 15 different serogroups of &lt;em&gt;L. pneumophila&lt;/em&gt;, only 5% of cases are ever confirmed by culture and &amp;gt;75% of known cases are caused by a single serogroup, SG1. It’s difficult to determine whether cases go unreported because diagnostic testing wasn’t performed or because a test (whether culture or antigen) failed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outcome of the criminal cases against former MDDHS employees could be the catalyst for policies to protect public utilities consumers from water-borne pathogens such as &lt;em&gt;Legionella&lt;/em&gt;. As it stands, water suppliers (e.g., municipal water systems) must monitor several water parameters, such as chlorine, on a weekly basis, but chlorine has a half-life of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www3.epa.gov/pesticides/chem_search/reg_actions/reregistration/fs_PC-020501_1-Feb-99.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;less than five hours&lt;/a&gt;, or even less in higher temperatures. This means that locations further away from municipal treatment plants, and places where water is stored, especially at warm temperatures such as in water heaters, are at increased risk of legionellae growth. While municipal water systems are also required to monitor water for bacteria that might cause gastrointestinal illnesses (e.g., &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt;), there are no federal laws for water-borne respiratory pathogens such as legionellae. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thelegionnaireslawyer.com/legionnaires-disease-determining-liability/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Legal liability&lt;/a&gt; for outbreaks of Legionnaires’ disease currently falls on the owners/operators of the facility at which the patient was exposed, as well as those responsible for installation and maintenance of the contaminated reservoir.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-figure-3-cases-of-legionnaires-disease-have-more-than-quadrupled-over-the-last-15-years-sourcehttpswwwcdcgovlegionelladownloadsfs-legionella-clinicianspdf&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Figure 3. Cases of Legionnaires’ disease have more than quadrupled over the last 15 years. [Source](https://www.cdc.gov/legionella/downloads/fs-legionella-clinicians.pdf)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/examining-flint/image_3_hudbaf0193182dbae1d39ff24f16f318be_44737_596e3775c917f130fc9290714dab3afb.webp 400w,
               /post/examining-flint/image_3_hudbaf0193182dbae1d39ff24f16f318be_44737_3792daece8945fe82e14d1069d274100.webp 760w,
               /post/examining-flint/image_3_hudbaf0193182dbae1d39ff24f16f318be_44737_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://akhagan.com/post/examining-flint/image_3_hudbaf0193182dbae1d39ff24f16f318be_44737_596e3775c917f130fc9290714dab3afb.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;541&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Figure 3. Cases of Legionnaires’ disease have more than quadrupled over the last 15 years. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cdc.gov/legionella/downloads/fs-legionella-clinicians.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Policy changes would come none too soon. Reported cases of Legionnaires’ disease in the U.S. have increased by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cdc.gov/legionella/downloads/fs-legionella-clinicians.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;four and half times&lt;/a&gt; over the last 15 years and fewer &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.micro.54.1.567&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;than 5%&lt;/a&gt; of cases are outbreak related with the vast majority occurring sporadically. But proper surveillance of legionellae levels in the water supply, along with the already collected chlorine data, are needed for researchers to understand the prevalence of legionellae and the efficacy of chlorine as a disinfectant. While exposure to 0.4 mg/liter of chlorine for 15 minutes is sufficient to kill legionellae in the lab, Zahran et al. point out that it may not be effective against legionellae contained within amoebas or biofilms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Swanson is carrying forward her research in Flint by working with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www8.nationalacademies.org/cp/CommitteeView.aspx?key=DELS-WSTB-16-02&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;team of experts&lt;/a&gt; at the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine to write a public report on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dels.nas.edu/Study-In-Progress/Management-Legionella-Water-Systems/DELS-WSTB-16-02&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;management of legionellae in water systems&lt;/a&gt;. In addition to surveying the current literature regarding legionellae ecology, human exposure, and management strategies, this white paper will also review current policies and hopefully make helpful recommendations for policy makers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Republished from ASM.org with permission.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Poisoning to Pharmacy: A Tale of Two Ergots</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/post/a-tale-of-two-ergots/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/post/a-tale-of-two-ergots/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Train Your T Cell(s): The Hidden World</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/post/how-to-train-your-t-cells/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/post/how-to-train-your-t-cells/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If You Give a Baby a Bath, and More Microbial Myths</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/post/give-a-baby-a-bath/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/post/give-a-baby-a-bath/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Is the five second rule real? Is your urine sterile? And do bacterial cells outnumber your own cells 10:1? These were some of the persistent microbial myths addressed in the video, “Microbial Myths.” Dr. Michael Schmidt and I began the discussion with some ASM history, after which Dr. Michael Schmidt explained the facts behind the 5-second rule and addressed other questions in depth. We followed this with a lightning round for short answers on some big questions, and the session wrapped with Dr. Schmidt on the spot as he accepted questions from the live audience at ASM Microbe 2018 in Atlanta, Ga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/04mxWViZn5I&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lightning round was fun but fast, and didn’t allow in-depth answers to a complex question, nor did we have time to address all of the questions from the audience. Let’s dive into the studies surrounding those questions here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;you-can-sanitize-your-sponge-in-the-microwave-verdict-myth&#34;&gt;You can sanitize your sponge in the microwave. Verdict: MYTH&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kitchen sponges are the perfect breeding ground for bacteria: they’re warm and moist after use; they’re covered in pores that trap water and provide surfaces for bacteria to replicate; they come in contact with contaminated surfaces (like moldy food dishes and chicken-laden cutting boards), and they’re used for weeks or months at a time. This perfect storm makes it no surprise that sponges harbor more bacteria than anywhere else &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nsf.org/newsroom_pdf/journal_of_envir_health_sept_2012_microbial_hotspots.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tested&lt;/a&gt; in the average home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several products and techniques claim to sanitize your kitchen sponges, so they can be “safely” reused. For instance, a Google search for “ways to sanitize a sponge” brought up websites suggested microwaving, vinegar, and bleach as some of the most prevalent DIY techniques to extend the lifespan of a sponge. But do these techniques work?&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-figure-1-a-microscopic-image-of-bacteria-fluorescing-on-a-sponge-red-b-surface-of-the-sponge-blue-c-overlay-of-fluorescent-bacteria-and-sponge-d-3-d-rendering-of-bacteria-red-on-the-surface-of-a-sponge-blue-scale-bar--10µm-sourcehttpwwwdxdoiorg101038s41598-017-06055-9&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Figure 1. A) Microscopic image of bacteria fluorescing on a sponge (red) B) Surface of the sponge (blue) C) Overlay of fluorescent bacteria and sponge. D) 3-D rendering of bacteria (red) on the surface of a sponge (blue) (Scale bar = 10µm). [Source](http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1038/s41598-017-06055-9).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/give-a-baby-a-bath/image_1_huef798db85978885c7c3e4621f1bfa220_4004465_42862f2f6f51d388bad2ed14ffc4b98b.webp 400w,
               /post/give-a-baby-a-bath/image_1_huef798db85978885c7c3e4621f1bfa220_4004465_72ff96c00178417863af93e02da812d7.webp 760w,
               /post/give-a-baby-a-bath/image_1_huef798db85978885c7c3e4621f1bfa220_4004465_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://akhagan.com/post/give-a-baby-a-bath/image_1_huef798db85978885c7c3e4621f1bfa220_4004465_42862f2f6f51d388bad2ed14ffc4b98b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;673&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Figure 1. A) Microscopic image of bacteria fluorescing on a sponge (red) B) Surface of the sponge (blue) C) Overlay of fluorescent bacteria and sponge. D) 3-D rendering of bacteria (red) on the surface of a sponge (blue) (Scale bar = 10µm). &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1038/s41598-017-06055-9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While studying the types of bacteria commonly found on sponges, a &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-017-06055-9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;2017 study&lt;/a&gt; touched on this question. Using microscopy techniques, the researchers visualized bacteria growing inside the pores of 14 used kitchen sponges and found high bacterial counts (~10^7^ to 10^9^ cfus per sponge). DNA sequencing showed that about 36% of the bacteria on sponges belonged to the family Moraxellaceae, which is a common member of the skin microbiome. Other prevalent taxa were &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonadaceae&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhizobiaceae&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Flavobacteriaceae&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcaceae&lt;/em&gt;. Some taxa, such as &lt;em&gt;Xanthomonadaceae&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Enterobacteriaceae&lt;/em&gt;, varied according to the sponge tested, which might reflect the habits and food choices of the previous owners. &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1155/2016/1659784&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Another study&lt;/a&gt; also found &lt;em&gt;Bacillus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Micrococcus&lt;/em&gt; to be prevalent on kitchen sponges. Potentially pathogenic bacteria seem to comprise only a small portion of the bacteria found on a sponge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can sanitizing your sponge eliminate these bacteria? In the &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-017-06055-9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;2017 study above&lt;/a&gt;, previous owners of some of the collected sponges reported to have “cleaned” their sponges regularly (either microwaving or rinsing with hot water). Despite cleaning, these sponges contained the same number of bacteria as non-sanitized sponges, but the makeup of the bacterial communities differed. Sponge sanitation clearly doesn’t kill all of the bacteria present on a sponge, and any surviving bacteria can quickly take over sponge real estate. This is due to the high numbers of bacteria that colonize the sponge surface: even if microwaving were to kill 99.9% of 10^7^ bacteria, almost 10,000 are still alive!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of sanitizing the sponge, microwaving or using other techniques may predispose a sponge to harboring heartier bacterial species. Your best bet is to &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1080/09603120050127202&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;rinse the sponge&lt;/a&gt; daily and replace it all together on a weekly basis or after wiping up raw egg or meat. If you’re concerned about the environmental impact of this suggestion, consider purchasing dye-free, biodegradable &lt;a href=&#34;http://twistclean.com/products/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;sponges&lt;/a&gt; or using dishrags that can be frequently washed and dried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;delaying-babys-first-bath-helps-establish-the-skin-microbiome-verdict-probably-true&#34;&gt;Delaying baby’s first bath helps establish the skin microbiome. Verdict: Probably TRUE&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Newborn babies are covered with vernix caseosa, a thick Vaseline-like layer that protects their fragile skin from moisture &lt;em&gt;in utero&lt;/em&gt; and contains antibacterial enzymes such as lysozyme. On top of this, the birthing process coats newborns in blood and other bodily fluids, which might be contaminated with blood borne pathogens such as HIV and Hepatitis C. These fluids, along with the vernix, are wiped away following birth and the newborn is bathed as soon as possible, in part to &lt;a href=&#34;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/373017&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;protect hospital staff&lt;/a&gt; from blood borne pathogens. The World Health Organization suggests that baby’s first bath should be &lt;a href=&#34;https://insights.ovid.com/crossref?an=00149525-201610001-00003&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;postponed for 24 hours&lt;/a&gt; to prevent hypothermia, but many U.S. hospitals bathe the infant around eight hours post-birth unless the parents request otherwise. The life-threatening issue of hypothermia has guided much of the research and recommendations for infant bathing thus far. Only recently has research begun addressing the long-term impacts of bathing infants on the skin microbiome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newborn skin microbiome generally establishes within 4-6 days and coincides with maturation of the newborn skin to retain water and block absorption of chemicals. The establishment of the microbiome can be tracked by a decrease in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1046/j.1523-536x.2001.00161.x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;skin pH from 6.34 to 4.95&lt;/a&gt;. So far, the data indicate that the newborn skin microbiome &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org/content/107/26/11971&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;starts out&lt;/a&gt; the same in all areas of the body and most closely reflects the microbiome it was initially exposed to, whether that be the vaginal or skin (due to C-section). Over time, the skin microbiome composition &lt;a href=&#34;https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0022202X15350363&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;becomes site specific&lt;/a&gt; and gradually becomes more like the adult skin microbiome as the child ages. As with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.asm.org/index.php/general-science-blog/item/461-i-can-t-eat-that-or-how-our-microbiome-influences-our-dietary-restrictions&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;ust=1533211473759000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNEGqwPvqIbJV49nuEFfcKDP3eCnWQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;gut microbiome&lt;/a&gt;, the skin microbiome has a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5568566/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;role in human health&lt;/a&gt; by protecting against potential pathogens, immune regulation, and alterations in the microbiome implicated in skin conditions such as eczema.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-figure-2-a-graph-showing-the-number-of-bacterial-colonies-grown-from-swabs-taken-of-newborns-from-birth-to-24-hours-baths-were-given-at-one-hour-sourcehttpsdoiorg101002path1700950113&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Figure 2. A graph showing the number of bacterial colonies grown from swabs taken of newborns from birth to 24 hours. Baths were given at one hour. [Source](https://doi.org/10.1002/path.1700950113).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/give-a-baby-a-bath/image_2_hu005f492c50f164bfc145d9a00e8b1738_502795_9c3c0f53759285f68ee8adbe9a86efc4.webp 400w,
               /post/give-a-baby-a-bath/image_2_hu005f492c50f164bfc145d9a00e8b1738_502795_1063086046aee14a70d61dcb436672de.webp 760w,
               /post/give-a-baby-a-bath/image_2_hu005f492c50f164bfc145d9a00e8b1738_502795_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://akhagan.com/post/give-a-baby-a-bath/image_2_hu005f492c50f164bfc145d9a00e8b1738_502795_9c3c0f53759285f68ee8adbe9a86efc4.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;663&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Figure 2. A graph showing the number of bacterial colonies grown from swabs taken of newborns from birth to 24 hours. Baths were given at one hour. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/path.1700950113&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What effect, if any, does baby’s first bath have on establishment of the microbiome? A &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/path.1700950113&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;1968 study&lt;/a&gt;, suggests that the number and types of bacteria present on the skin (as grown on agar) are not significantly changed by bathing in soap and water. Close examination of the graph, however, reveals that bacterial counts at most body sites drop at the bathing time (one hour post birth) then quickly recover. These results were replicated by &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1523-536x.2001.00161.x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a 2001 study&lt;/a&gt; that compared the bacteria recovered from the skin of newborns immediately before their first bath in either water or mild soap and water, then one hour and 24 hours later. However, both of these studies relied on culturable bacteria to make their conclusions and there don’t seem to be any similar sequencing-based studies on full term infants to either confirm or refute their claims. Additionally, the impacts of bathing on the microbiome &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1038/sj.jp.7211332&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;seem to vary&lt;/a&gt; for pre-term infants, particularly since they are most likely to be bathed using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1097/ANC.0000000000000336&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;antimicrobials&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we know about the human microbiome in general, suggests that baby’s first bath would have an impact on the establishment of the skin microbiome. Along those lines, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1097/NMC.0000000000000374&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;recent article&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;em&gt;American Journal of Maternal/Child Nursing&lt;/em&gt; makes some practical suggestions for safeguarding the establishing microbiome in a healthy, full-term infant. First, initiate immediate skin-to-skin contact and limit handling of the newborn by non-family members. It isn’t necessary to either completely remove the protective vernix or to give daily baths. Finally, ensure that only water or mild cleaning products are used on baby’s skin. It’s clear that more research is needed to completely resolve the impact of baby’s first bath on the skin microbiome, but for now we consider this microbial myth “probably true”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;all-steps-of-aseptic-technique-are-essential-verdict-its-complicated&#34;&gt;All steps of aseptic technique are essential. Verdict: It’s complicated&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aseptic techniques originate from the labs of &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007%2Fs12045-007-0003-8.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pasteur&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://dx.doi.org/10.1017%2Fmdh.2012.22&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Koch&lt;/a&gt;. These researchers developed many of the methodologies and techniques still used today by microbiologists. Isolating bacteria on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.asm.org/index.php/general-science-blog/item/5895-women-in-science&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;agar plates&lt;/a&gt;, boiling as a form of sterilization (aka pasteurization), Koch’s postulates, and aseptic technique still prevail. Together, their experiments showed that microbes are all around us, on every surface we touch, and even in the air we breathe. Thus, to prevent contaminating their work, microbiologists take special precautions to protect their samples from environmental contaminants. Enter aseptic techniques:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sterilize media and tools by autoclave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wash your hands and disinfect the working surface to reduce the number of possible contaminants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Light a Bunsen burner that creates an upward draft of air to prevent contaminants in the air from settling on the work surface below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use that burner to sterilize tools such as inoculating loops and the opening of the tube or media bottle (just in case your loop accidentally touches).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the dogma taught in every microbiology course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both my undergraduate and masters research were done in a lab that strictly adhered to all steps of aseptic technique, and still got the odd contaminated agar plate or bottle of broth. On the other hand, my doctoral research was done in a lab where I worked at a bench without ever lighting a Bunsen burner. The change in protocol was weird at first, but quickly became the new norm after contamination turned out to be less of an issue that I had anticipated. So the personal experiences of researchers like myself (and the audience member who suggested this myth) raise questions about whether some of these techniques are truly necessary at the lab bench.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why might the experiences of contemporary microbiologists differ from Pasteur and Koch? In part, most early experiments on contamination from airborne microbes involved extensive exposure of the media to open air (e.g., beer in fermenting vats or broth sitting on a bench for days). Conversely, the brief exposure of a media bottle to the air when removing a bit of broth may not require the sterile airspace provided by a Bunsen burner, particularly since that airspace is very easily disturbed by rapid movement.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-figure-3-a-set-up-for-aseptic-technique-in-a-microbiology-lab-with-a-bunsen-burner-inoculating-loop-and-agar-plates-sourcehttpscommonswikimediaorgwikifileinoculating_bacteria_in_a_college_microbiology_labjpg-b-tabletop-incinerator-for-inoculating-loops-sourcehttpscommonswikimediaorgwikifilebacti-cineratorjpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Figure 3. A) Set up for aseptic technique in a microbiology lab with a Bunsen burner, inoculating loop, and agar plates. [Source](https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Inoculating_bacteria_in_a_college_microbiology_lab.jpg). B) Tabletop incinerator for inoculating loops. [Source](https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Bacti-Cinerator.jpeg).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/give-a-baby-a-bath/image_3_hucf2357e0c90907a0634da33ec615ed52_2106445_c7bf26320f3c05c19a2bc99312900145.webp 400w,
               /post/give-a-baby-a-bath/image_3_hucf2357e0c90907a0634da33ec615ed52_2106445_e1bfcc23e4239ef36f8994a17985a1ab.webp 760w,
               /post/give-a-baby-a-bath/image_3_hucf2357e0c90907a0634da33ec615ed52_2106445_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://akhagan.com/post/give-a-baby-a-bath/image_3_hucf2357e0c90907a0634da33ec615ed52_2106445_c7bf26320f3c05c19a2bc99312900145.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;569&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Figure 3. A) Set up for aseptic technique in a microbiology lab with a Bunsen burner, inoculating loop, and agar plates. &lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Inoculating_bacteria_in_a_college_microbiology_lab.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;. B) Tabletop incinerator for inoculating loops. &lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Bacti-Cinerator.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, many research labs now use pre-sterilized disposable tools to transfer media and bacterial cultures instead of reusable inoculating loops, a process &lt;a href=&#34;http://aem.asm.org/content/16/8/1146.short&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;known to create aerosols&lt;/a&gt; that may increase potential air contaminants. (A reason why some labs use bench top incinerators.) In other words, perhaps using a Bunsen burner to flame a loop, creates the need for the sterile airspace underneath the burner flame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I haven’t been able to uncover any research specifically addressing whether all steps of the aseptic technique dogma are absolutely necessary (if you know of one, please post it below!). Instead, aseptic technique has become so canonized in microbiology that I found a &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/9780471729259.mca04ds11&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;protocol paper&lt;/a&gt; published in &lt;em&gt;Current Protocols in Microbiology&lt;/em&gt; that had zero citations. Zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think there’s enough history to indicate that many steps of aseptic technique are indeed essential, but there are also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quora.com/To-what-extent-does-working-near-a-Bunsen-burner-when-working-with-bacteria-actually-maintain-a-sterile-bench&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;enough questions&lt;/a&gt; to welcome a study of the contributions of flaming techniques to maintaining an aseptic workspace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you have any Microbial Myths that haven’t been addressed? Comment below and maybe I’ll do another follow up! Now, if you’ll excuse me, I need to go replace my kitchen sponge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Republished from ASM.org with permission&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Invasive Fungal Infections: A Creeping Public Health Threat</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/post/invasive-fungal-infections/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/post/invasive-fungal-infections/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Old Wives’ Tales and Garlic as an Antibiotic: Are Microbial Myths Fact or Fiction?</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/post/old-wives-tales-and-garlic-as-an-antibiotic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/post/old-wives-tales-and-garlic-as-an-antibiotic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Probing the Depths of Life</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/post/probing-the-depths-of-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/post/probing-the-depths-of-life/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Siderophores: A treatment target?</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/post/siderophore-treatment-target/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/post/siderophore-treatment-target/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In previous Microbial Science blog posts, I described how many bacterial pathogens rely on siderophores to help &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.asm.org/index.php/general-science-blog/item/6411-siderophores-bacterial-iron-scavengers&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;scavenge iron&lt;/a&gt; during infections as well as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.asm.org/index.php/general-science-blog/item/6628-siderophores-bacterial-swiss-army-knives&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;protect them&lt;/a&gt; from the immune response or competing bacterial species. But is there a way to take what we’ve learned about these essential molecules and use them to turn the tide against the wave of antibacterial resistance? Researchers are developing sideromycins, inhibitors and vaccines to turn siderophores against their makers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sideromycins&#34;&gt;Sideromycins&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get an edge in survival against competing bacterial species, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.asm.org/index.php/general-science-blog/item/6628-siderophores-bacterial-swiss-army-knives&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;some bacteria&lt;/a&gt; (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007/BF00249977.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/em&gt; spp.&lt;/a&gt;) make sideromycins, siderophores conjugated with an antibiotic molecule. Sideromycins look like siderophores to other species of bacteria, which import them for their iron payload. But by bringing sideromycins in, the bacteria inadvertently &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10534-008-9199-7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;poison themselves&lt;/a&gt; with the attached antibiotic. Researchers have caught onto this trick and designed their own sideromycins to target bacterial pathogens. This is important work since antibacterial resistance is at an all-time high and the number of effective antibiotics is decreasing. Since most resistance mechanisms rely on keeping the antibiotics out, the Trojan Horse sideromycins might help antibiotics bypass these and target specific pathogens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what researchers at the University of Notre Dame had in mind when they &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.7b00102&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;designed a sideromycin&lt;/a&gt; against the multidrug-resistant &lt;em&gt;Acinetobacter baumannii&lt;/em&gt;. The authors conjugated the antibiotic daptomycin to the &lt;em&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/em&gt; siderophore called fimsbactin and effectively treated infected mice. This is especially exciting because daptomycin is traditionally only effective against gram-positive bacteria, but by conjugating it to fimsbactin, they could use it to treat the gram-negative &lt;em&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/em&gt;, but not others (e.g., &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/em&gt;). Other groups have generated sideromycins against &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1021/bc300610f&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/jpp/article/65/4/512/6133002&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Providencia stuartii&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.2174/1568026013395524&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and even &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1021/jm400265k&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A. baumannii&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but this report is the first to show that the drugs can work in a mouse infection model. And unfortunately, it is possible for mechanisms to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.00205-06&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;prevent sideromycin import&lt;/a&gt; to evolve, thus creating resistance against sideromycins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;inhibitors&#34;&gt;Inhibitors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to co-opt our knowledge of siderophores is to generate new antibiotics that target siderophores and prevent their production or use by pathogens. There are two common pathways for siderophore biosynthesis in bacteria, and researchers have taken advantage of these similarities to identify small molecules that interact with and inhibit siderophore biosynthesis enzymes. In some cases, researchers use rational design to generate these small molecules. By taking what they know about the structure of the enzymes and how they function, researchers can generate small molecules that they think will act as inhibitors. Two 2005 studies described how researchers targeted an early step in siderophore biosynthesis by &lt;em&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/em&gt;. One group designed molecules that interfered with a biosynthetic &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1021/jm051060o&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;protein’s ability to bind ATP&lt;/a&gt;, while the other &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1038/nchembio706&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;targeted the ligand binding site&lt;/a&gt; of a biosynthetic protein and was also able to inhibit siderophore biosynthesis by &lt;em&gt;Yersinia pestis&lt;/em&gt;. More recently, Dr. David Sherman’s lab at the University of Michigan &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1021/ja4115924&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;screened a library&lt;/a&gt; of naturally occurring small molecules for their ability to inhibit siderophore biosynthesis in &lt;em&gt;Bacillus anthracis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/em&gt;. In all of these cases, the identified molecules inhibited growth of the pathogen in a test tube, but none have been tested in a mouse model of infection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;vaccines&#34;&gt;Vaccines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to fight an infection is by preventing it from happening at all. With that in mind, Dr. Harry Mobley’s lab at the University of Michigan has been exploring siderophore-based vaccines against urinary tract infections. Initially, they tried to target the immune response against select siderophore receptors on the cell surface of urinary pathogenic &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; (UPEC). With this method, they successfully vaccinated mice against the receptor for yersiniabactin and generate a protective immune response. But those proteins are unwieldy and difficult to purify for regular use in a vaccine. What about targeting the siderophore itself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generating protective vaccines that target siderophores has been considered a risky prospect since the molecules are so small and don’t seem to elicit immune responses. While a 2009 study demonstrated it was possible to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1021/jm900119q&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;generate antibodies against a siderophore&lt;/a&gt; (in this case vibriobactin), they didn’t show a protective immune response. But two papers published side-by-side in the &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt; last year showed how researchers have accomplished targeting the mouse immune response against siderophores. One study from the Mobley lab described their continued efforts to generate a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1606324113&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;vaccine against UPEC&lt;/a&gt;. Here, they conjugated the siderophores aerobactin and yersiniabactin to cationized bovine serum albumin—albumin protein modified to elicit a strong immune response—and successfully immunized mice against urinary tract infections. Unfortunately, Mobley’s group wasn’t able to demonstrate protective antibodies against the siderophores. According to the study’s first author Dr. Laura Mike, “it is possible that siderophores are stimulating the immune system in other ways; the small size of the siderophores are not as amenable to many of the standard immunological assays.” This makes it difficult to identify the type of immune response the mice were generating as a result of the vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the second study, from Manuela Raffatellu’s lab at the University of California, Irvine, did &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1606290113&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;detect antibodies against enterobactin&lt;/a&gt;, the siderophore of vaccination. Raffatellu’s group also conjugated the siderophore to an immunogenic protein but used cholera toxin subunit B because it helps elicit a strong mucosal response, which is important for protection against &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt;. Raffatellu’s group was also successful in generating a vaccine that protected against the pathogen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s especially promising, according to Dr. Mike, is that these studies have shown that it may not be necessary to conjugate the siderophore to the immunogenic protein, and that these vaccines had little effect on the mice microbiomes. So, in theory, researchers could “pick any virulence-associated siderophore for a vaccine antigen. We will still have to keep in mind that not all species of bacteria, or isolates within a single species, always use the same exact siderophores,” Mike says. But this offers a way to tailor the vaccine because “we can either create very narrow-spectrum vaccines by only using one or two siderophore antigens, or we could create a broader vaccine by incorporating more siderophores into our formulation,” she adds&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research into anti-siderophore treatment strategies appears promising. But none of them have been translated to an effective treatment has emerged from this work, and few of the putative therapy options have been tested in mice. This is an expensive step, but is necessary to identify which of these therapies have potential for clinical use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Republished from ASM.org with permission&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Siderophores: Bacterial Swiss Army knives</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/post/siderophore-bacterial-swiss-army-knives/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/post/siderophore-bacterial-swiss-army-knives/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Siderophores are small molecules that bacteria primarily use to scavenge for iron in their environment. But siderophores can do double duty, with functions in survival, attack, and signalling, making these molecules bacterial Swiss Army knives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;survival&#34;&gt;Survival&lt;/h2&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-figure-1-part-of-the-periodic-table-highlighting-some-of-the-elements-shown-to-be-bound-by-siderophores-those-highlighted-in-green-mn-fe-zn-are-essential-for-growth-and-those-in-yellow-b-si-cu-are-helpful-for-survival-or-signaling-sourcehttpscommonswikimediaorgwikifile3aperiodic-tablejpg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Figure 1. Part of the periodic table highlighting some of the elements shown to be bound by siderophores. Those highlighted in green (Mn, Fe, Zn) are essential for growth and those in yellow (B, Si, Cu) are helpful for survival or signaling. [Source](https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3APeriodic-table.jpg).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/siderophore-bacterial-swiss-army-knives/image_1_hu0127ec15ef3f1cfe294f205c261d26af_556208_60b3c75b33a421fdfba14d7a5e9e45f5.webp 400w,
               /post/siderophore-bacterial-swiss-army-knives/image_1_hu0127ec15ef3f1cfe294f205c261d26af_556208_1ff85b5601fe1f93f885544f9e6c1c8c.webp 760w,
               /post/siderophore-bacterial-swiss-army-knives/image_1_hu0127ec15ef3f1cfe294f205c261d26af_556208_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://akhagan.com/post/siderophore-bacterial-swiss-army-knives/image_1_hu0127ec15ef3f1cfe294f205c261d26af_556208_60b3c75b33a421fdfba14d7a5e9e45f5.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;386&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Figure 1. Part of the periodic table highlighting some of the elements shown to be bound by siderophores. Those highlighted in green (Mn, Fe, Zn) are essential for growth and those in yellow (B, Si, Cu) are helpful for survival or signaling. &lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3APeriodic-table.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Fig]The affinity of siderophores for iron occurs along a spectrum from high to low, and where a siderophore falls on this spectrum can alter their potential to bind other elements. In the last siderophore post, we learned that siderophores can import essential nutrients other than iron like manganese or zinc. But siderophores can also bind non-essential nutrients, as occurs with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1039/c3cc44437f&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;silicon-binding enterobactin&lt;/a&gt; found in the root system of a Cameroonian medicinal plant. This silicon-binding ability doesn’t seem to benefit the producing &lt;em&gt;Streptomyces&lt;/em&gt; species, but likely acts as a cooperative molecule that provides the silicon its plant host requires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some siderophores can also bind copper, not for growth, but for survival by decreasing toxic quantities to manageable ones. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.R111.316406&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Copper is toxic&lt;/a&gt; to bacteria, capable of killing methicillin-resistant &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/em&gt; within 90 minutes (they can survive 72 hours on stainless steel). Copper binds to cellular proteins, altering their structure and thus their ability to function. And like iron, copper has redox potential so it can also undergo the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8597169&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fenton reaction&lt;/a&gt;, taking or trading electrons between Cu^1+^ and Cu^2+^ to generate hydroxyl radicals (negatively charged oxygen species like OH- or OH˙ that damage DNA).&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-figure-2-enterobactin-uses-catechols-red-to-bind-iron-and-copper-sourcehttpsenwikipediaorgwikienterobactinmediafileenterobactinsvg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Figure 2. Enterobactin uses catechols (red) to bind iron and copper. [Source](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enterobactin#/media/File:Enterobactin.svg).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/siderophore-bacterial-swiss-army-knives/image_2_hu7d64e64286a1d3c60e0f716750226049_24996_54191b8c59121213f5ca243b82e325ac.webp 400w,
               /post/siderophore-bacterial-swiss-army-knives/image_2_hu7d64e64286a1d3c60e0f716750226049_24996_921ed848e8e80b149d691aad5461b357.webp 760w,
               /post/siderophore-bacterial-swiss-army-knives/image_2_hu7d64e64286a1d3c60e0f716750226049_24996_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://akhagan.com/post/siderophore-bacterial-swiss-army-knives/image_2_hu7d64e64286a1d3c60e0f716750226049_24996_54191b8c59121213f5ca243b82e325ac.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;584&#34;
               height=&#34;522&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Figure 2. Enterobactin uses catechols (red) to bind iron and copper. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enterobactin#/media/File:Enterobactin.svg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yersiniabactin is one siderophore that can &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jbc.org/content/290/31/18967.full.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;bind copper&lt;/a&gt;, defending against both copper toxicity and reactive oxygen species. Enterobactin can also bind copper, but only after oxidation of the siderophore by the protein &lt;a href=&#34;https://jb.asm.org/content/186/17/5826.short&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CueO&lt;/a&gt;. Enterobactin binds iron using three structural features called catechol rings (circled in Fig. 2). If these rings are left unoxidized in the non-iron-bound-siderophore they can reduce copper, which worsens toxicity. By oxidizing enterobactin, CueO both helps the siderophore bind toxic copper and prevents it from becoming more toxic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both copper and reactive oxygen species are encountered by infection-causing bacteria within macrophages, which use those methods to kill invaders. Two siderophores that use catechol rings to bind iron, salmochelin and enterobactin, can &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1042/BJ20121771&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;protect bacteria against the “oxidative burst”&lt;/a&gt;. The catch is that they must be inside the cell. The &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus&lt;/em&gt; siderophore &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00284-014-0567-y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;staphyloferrin B&lt;/a&gt; also protects against reactive oxygen species, but siderophores that lack catechols, such as yersiniabactin and aerobactin, aren’t protective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;signaling&#34;&gt;Signaling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, yersiniabactin appears to act as a signaling molecule with the immune response. The siderophore has been shown to help &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1128/mBio.01397-16&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Klebsiella pneumoniae&lt;/em&gt; infections spread&lt;/a&gt; and increase inflammation (which increases the production of reactive oxygen species). Other siderophores act as signals to cells of either the same or differing bacterial species. Researchers have also found &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1021/ja073788v&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;boron-bound siderophores&lt;/a&gt; in seawater, where boron is quite common. Since bacteria don’t require boron and the boron-siderophore structure is different from iron-bound siderophore, the authors suggest that they function as signaling molecules instead of scavengers. Perhaps their signalling function is similar to pseudomonad &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.092016999&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;pyoverdine, which helps to regulate&lt;/a&gt; its own production, as well as that of other proteins like toxins.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-figure-3-when-_e-coli_-and-_b-subtilis_-are-grown-on-agar-together-top-left-_b-subtilis_-begins-sporulation-indicated-by-the-expression-of-fluorescent-proteins-bottom-left-however-culturing-_b-subtilis_-with-_b-circulans_-top-right-doesnt-induce-sporulation-bottom-right-source-fig-1httpaemasmorgcontent8310e03293-16f1expansionhtml&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Figure 3. When _E. coli_ and _B. subtilis_ are grown on agar together (top left), _B. subtilis_ begins sporulation indicated by the expression of fluorescent proteins (bottom left). However, culturing _B. subtilis_ with _B. circulans_ (top right), doesn&amp;#39;t induce sporulation (bottom right). [Source, Fig. 1](http://aem.asm.org/content/83/10/e03293-16/F1.expansion.html).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/siderophore-bacterial-swiss-army-knives/image_3_hu10e992dc02527ec7ed4b641d78ec81e8_992851_b18b327e005462e135101d4222990078.webp 400w,
               /post/siderophore-bacterial-swiss-army-knives/image_3_hu10e992dc02527ec7ed4b641d78ec81e8_992851_e93021f1b02cc587a4408231a065fd91.webp 760w,
               /post/siderophore-bacterial-swiss-army-knives/image_3_hu10e992dc02527ec7ed4b641d78ec81e8_992851_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://akhagan.com/post/siderophore-bacterial-swiss-army-knives/image_3_hu10e992dc02527ec7ed4b641d78ec81e8_992851_b18b327e005462e135101d4222990078.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;412&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Figure 3. When &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/em&gt; are grown on agar together (top left), &lt;em&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/em&gt; begins sporulation indicated by the expression of fluorescent proteins (bottom left). However, culturing &lt;em&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;em&gt;B. circulans&lt;/em&gt; (top right), doesn&amp;rsquo;t induce sporulation (bottom right). &lt;a href=&#34;http://aem.asm.org/content/83/10/e03293-16/F1.expansion.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Source, Fig. 1&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some strains of bacteria belonging to the Firmicute phylum, such as &lt;em&gt;Clostridia&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Bacillus&lt;/em&gt;, form endospores. Endospores are like survival pods that enable the bacteria to survive harsh conditions. The process of endospore formation (sporulation) occurs in response to environmental signals, such as low nutrient levels. Recently, researchers have identified another one, siderophores. When &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.1128/AEM.03293-16&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; imports siderophores produced by other species (e.g., enterobactin from &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt;), this triggers sporulation. Sporulation frees up resources for &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; but enables long-term survival for &lt;em&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;striking&#34;&gt;Striking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The poaching of siderophores by non-producing bacterial species (such as enterobactin import by &lt;em&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/em&gt;) is common in the microbial world. But siderophores are not always what they appear to be—and bear more than metallic gifts. &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubs.rsc.org/en/content/articlelanding/2015/DT/C4DT03559C&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sideromycins&lt;/a&gt; are siderophores linked to antibiotics, their import by microbial competitors inhibits protein synthesis, making siderophores the original Trojan Horse. Additionally, the pseudomonad siderophores pyochelin and pyoverdine can create hydroxyl radicals. This helps &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/em&gt; spp. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dx.doi.org/10.2217/17460913.2.4.387&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;degrade toxic molecules&lt;/a&gt; and perform other functions. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0046754&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pyochelin-produced&lt;/a&gt; reactive oxygen, for instance, can be used a weapon in interspecies warfare with &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt;. Of course, enterobactin can also help protect &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we’ve seen, siderophores are not limited to iron binding but have alternate functions that can range from cell signaling, to cooperative element scavenging, to oxidative stress protectors or even producers. Microbes even use siderophores as weapons against each other, taking advantage of their competitors’ need for iron. So are there ways to target these bacterial Swiss Army knives with antibiotic treatments and turn siderophores against their makers? Stay tuned for the final installment in the siderophore series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is Part 2 in a multipart post about bacterial siderophores. Next: &lt;a href=&#34;https://akhagan.com/post/siderophore-treatment-target/&#34;&gt;can humans develop treatments to exploit our knowledge of siderophores?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Republished from ASM.org with permission&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Suggestions for Improving Invited Speaker Diversity To Reflect Trainee Diversity</title>
      <link>https://akhagan.com/publication/suggestions-for-improving-invited-speaker-diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akhagan.com/publication/suggestions-for-improving-invited-speaker-diversity/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
